Finding Aid for the Los Angeles Urban League Records LSC.0203
UCLA Library Special Collections
Los Angeles Urban League records
1933-1945
UCLA Library Special Collections
Los Angeles Urban League
LSC.0203
1.0 linear feet (2 boxes)
The Los Angeles branch of the National Urban League stems from a 1921 organization founded by Katherine Barr and others who attended Booker T. Washington's Tuskegee Institute in Alabama. The league gathered information about racial discrimination against African Americans and other minorities in jobs, health services, and housing; helped develop fair employment programs during World War II, and was active in the formation of the City Human Relations Commission. The collection consists of correspondence and papers relating to African Americans, immigrant labor and problems of social planning in Los Angeles.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9922210523606533
Biography
The Los Angeles branch of the National Urban League stems from a 1921 organization founded by Katherine Barr and others who attended Booker T. Washington's Tuskegee Institute in Alabama; gathered information about racial discrimination against African Americans and other minorities in jobs, health services, and housing; helped develop fair employment programs during World War II, and was active in the formation of the City Human Relations Commission; membership changed from 90% black in 1970 to 40% Hispanic by the late 1990s; works in partnership with business and government to serve disadvantaged and poor people.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence and papers relating to African Americans, immigrant labor and problems of social planning in Los Angeles. Correspondents include Ralph Bunche, and papers include Carey McWilliams' Report on importation of Negro labor to California. Also contains forms related to the Carnegie-Myrdal study.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Los Angeles Urban League Records (2 items).
The same digitized items are also available through the Calisphere portal: Los Angeles Urban League Records (2 items).
African Americans -- California -- Los Angeles -- Economic conditions.; African Americans -- Employment -- California -- Los Angeles.; Los Angeles Urban League -- Archives
- [Research]
  - Research headings / resources, and unidentified typescript page, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bruce, Helen E. Occupations for Negro Women in Los Angeles, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bond, Max. A Study of the Need for Housing for Negro Women and girls, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Burch, Edward A. Civil Rights and the Negro, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Somerville, J.A. The Negro in California (Somerville Study), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Burch, Edward A. Change in the Outlook of the Negro Client Toward the Negro Worker, 1938. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Burger, Alice. Negro Labor Unions in the Transportation Industry in Los Angeles, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Burger, Alice. The Vocational Guidance and Training of Negro Youth in Los Angeles, 1938. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Glenn, Sollace, Harlem Artists Guild. Survey of Number of Negro Artists Employed by the Federal Art Project [Letter only], undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Evans, Roy. Negro Building and Spending Power of Los Angeles, California, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - O'Neal, Joseph B. Vocation and Industry, (?)., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lamb, Bonnie Theodora. Letter to [Exploratory Committee on Negro Welfare?], 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Council of Social Agencies of Los Angeles. Division of Family Welfare and Adult Services Subcommittee on the Negro Community. Findings, 1940.; (3 copies) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Holton, Karl. Deteriorating Zone Committee. Notes on the Negro Districts in Los Angeles ... including "Central Avenue" Area, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Eastside Labor's Protective Committee [Letterhead only], 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gooden, J.E. "What can Negroes Do Themselves, in the Los Angeles Area, to Help Create a More Respectful Attitude on Part of the White People of This Area" [questionnaire answer] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Jones, Lillian. The Negroes of Los Angeles, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Gowens, Norman C. Correspondence with Floyd Covington [Executive Director, Los Angeles Urban League] re "The Right Action,", 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Houston, Norman O. Survey on Negro Business and Businessmen, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Simmons, Herbert. National Urban League, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Institute of Social Research. Interview and survey instructions, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miller, Loren [Survey response?], undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - McWilliams, Carey. Report on Importation of Negro Labor to California. Division on Immigration and Housing, 1939-1942. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Baruch, Dorothy W. Resume and Guggenheim proposal, and related correspondence, 1943-1944. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Floyd Covington / Charles S. Johnson (Fisk University) correspondence, 1940, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Covington, Floyd. Employment figures of Negroes in War Industries (letter dated April 6, 1943) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Covington, Floyd. Exploratory Survey Racial Tension Areas, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Floyd Covington / Charles Johnson (Fisk University) correspondence, 1943. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Taylor, Alfred Marie. Program Changes in Local Urban Leagues. Schedule and correspondence, 1943. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Covington, Floyd. Field Report, Trends of Race Relations, 1944. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Floyd Covington / Charles Johnson [Fisk University] correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Smith, William T. <The Negro in Hollywood, undated, [1937?]; (2 copies) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Floyd Covington / Carnegie Institute correspondence re The Negro in Motion Pictures, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Historical Background of Negro Survey, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Hart, LeRoy S. The Negro is L.A. County, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Negroes in Outstanding Positions and Who Have Achieved Much in the Several Fields of Business" (Charleston, West Virginia)--Letter form I.J.K. Wells and nomination form, 1936. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - National Urban League correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Carnegie-Myrdal Study, 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence from Ralph Bunche and questionnaire, 1939. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - The Carnegie-Myrdal study questionnaire, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Scope and Contents
      Questionnaire sent to Mr. Floyd C. Covington on the status of the Negro in the American life. Sent by Bunche in his capacity as staff member of the Carnegie-Myrdal Study of the Negro in America.
    - Letter, 1939 November 2, Washington D.C. to Mr. Floyd C. Covington, Los Angeles, California (Box 38, Folder 13)
      Cover letter to Mr. Covington from Bunche, Staff Member, Carnegie-Myrdal Study of the Negro in America. Bunche introduces the Carnegie Corporation which is sponsoring the survey on the status of the Negro in American life. Bunche requests that Covington please take the time to answer the questionnaire.
  - Outline and William Shapiro's Suggested Outline Negro Research Projects (California), 1940. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Form I - Community for which report is made, 1940? (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Form II - Political Activity Schedule, 1940? (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Form III - Recreation & Leisure Time Schedule, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Form IV - Survey of the Negro Wage Earner in Los Angeles, 1940? (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Form V - Negro Business & Businesses, 1940? (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Form VI - Relief and Housing, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Form VII - Churches & Lodges Schedule, (?), 1940 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Form VIII - Education, 1940? (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Form IX - Migration Schedule, 1940? (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Form X - Racial Attitudes Schedule, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Incomplete copy [of study], 1940? (Box 2, Folder 16)